<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About on Piotr Polak - cybersecurity and standardization expert</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/about/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About on Piotr Polak - cybersecurity and standardization expert</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Copyright 2026, Piotr Polak</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RED Delegated Act vs Cyber Resilience Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/red_da_vs_cra/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/red_da_vs_cra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Both EU regulations the Radio Equipment Directive &lt;a href=&#34;https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=uriserv%3AOJ.L_.2022.007.01.0006.01.ENG&amp;amp;toc=OJ%3AL%3A2022%3A007%3ATOC&#34;&gt;Delegated Act&lt;/a&gt; (RED DA) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2024/2847/oj/eng&#34;&gt;Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a&gt; (CRA) address digital product security. While their goal at first glance seems  to  bethe same they are fundamentally different in scope and focus.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The RED DA addresses security of radio equipment with radio interfaces that can communicate with the Internet. The focus of the RED DA is to protect networks (Article 3.3 d), personal data (Article 3.3 e) and financial data or transactions (Article 3.3 f). The priority here is not even the product security but to ensure that the product has the capabilities to ensure networks, user data and financial data or transactions are safeguarded.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The CRA supersedes RED DA and targets all products that have programmable components or connectivity capabilities including hardware and software regardless if they can connect to the Internet or not. This, for CRA, also includes &amp;ldquo;remote data processing&amp;rdquo; functionality at a distance for which the software is designed and developed by the manufacturer, or under manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s responsibility, and absence of which would prevent the product from performing one of its functions. The focus of the CRA is to ensure the products placed on the EU market are secure and maintain their security over their lifetime. The security risk assessment combined with appropriate processes is selected as the main tool to achieve that.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;assets&#34;&gt;Assets&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Another aspect that is different between the RED DA and CRA is what asset classes are required to be protected. RED DA requires protection of specific asset classes that reflect well all three articles (Article 3.3 d, e and f) that the RED DA activated:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Security assets&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Network assets&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Privacy assets&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Financial assets&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the RED DA, the CRA requires protection of any asset that, when compromised, may introduce a risk that can not be tolerated and has to be mitigated. Therefore, identification of all product related assets and execution of the security risk assessment for each of the identified assets is required.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;processes&#34;&gt;Processes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Another fundamental difference between the RED DA and CRA is that RED DA does not set any process related requirements. The RED DA only specifies capabilities that a product is required to have at the time of placement on the EU market.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In contrast, CRA extends the manufacturer responsibility to the entire product life cycle. The focus of CRA is on processes that ensure that security risk assessment of the product and the mitigation of identified risks is performed on regular basis over the product lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;product-assessment-and-compliance&#34;&gt;Product assessment and compliance&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The harmonized standards such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cencenelec.eu/news-events/news/2025/newsletter/ots-59-cybersecurity-standards/&#34;&gt;EN 18031-1/2/3&lt;/a&gt; allow, with some exceptions, for self-declaration under the RED DA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The CRA may require more rigorous assessment depending on the product’s classification. Important or critical products listed by the CRA may require third party assessment of an accredited test lab (&lt;a href=&#34;https://single-market-economy.ec.europa.eu/single-market/goods/building-blocks/notified-bodies_en&#34;&gt;Notified Body&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Manufacturers that have already performed the product assessment for the RED DA are expected to extend the scope of their assessment to cover all &lt;a href=&#34;http://piotrpolak.com/post/cra_overview/&#34;&gt;obligations of manufacturers&lt;/a&gt; defined by the CRA including not only the product security or capabilities but also consider process related requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-timeline&#34;&gt;The timeline&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cra_timeline.png&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The RED DA is enforced from 1st of August 2025 but is already &lt;a href=&#34;https://ec.europa.eu/info/law/better-regulation/have-your-say/initiatives/14766-Cybersecurity-repeal-of-Delegated-Regulation-supplementing-the-Radio-Equipment-Directive_en&#34;&gt;expected to be repealed&lt;/a&gt; the day the CRA is enforced which is 10th of December 2027.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;relevant-links&#34;&gt;Relevant links&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://piotrpolak.com/post/cra_overview&#34;&gt;Cyber Resilience Act overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2024/2847/oj/eng&#34;&gt;Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=uriserv%3AOJ.L_.2022.007.01.0006.01.ENG&amp;amp;toc=OJ%3AL%3A2022%3A007%3ATOC&#34;&gt;RED DA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cyber Resilience Act overview</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/cra_overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/cra_overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2024/2847/oj/eng&#34;&gt;Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a&gt; (CRA) EU regulation goal is to ensure the manufacturer employs appropriate processes ensuring the product is secure when placed on the EU market and the product security (compliance with the CRA) is maintained over the lifetime of the product.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-timeline&#34;&gt;The timeline&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cra_timeline.png&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The CRA establishes a phased implementation approach and will be activated in two steps. First step is planed to be activated in September of 2026 and imposes reporting obligations related to actively exploited vulnerabilities and serious security incidents, this include all products that are already placed on the EU market. The requirement to be fully complaint with the CRA will be activated in December 2027.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-scope&#34;&gt;The scope&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All products with digital elements including hardware, software and remote data processing (apps and cloud services the product depends on and is produced by the manufacture of the products) are in scope of the CRA with a few exceptions listed by the regulation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This effectively means any product that is capable of communication has to be evaluated for compliance with the CRA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;obligations-of-manufacturers&#34;&gt;Obligations of manufacturers&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The CRA introduces a number of obligations for compliance. The manufactures must ensure:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The product is compliant with all essential requirements related to product security and vulnerability handling&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Product cybersecurity risk analysis is performed and documented on regular basis over the product support period&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Due diligence when integrating components is exercised to ensure cybersecurity risks that may be introduced by the components are understood and if necessary mitigated&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Relevant cybersecurity aspects concerning the product are documented and sufficient information is provided to third parties (including know vulnerabilities)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vulnerabilities are handled during the product support period&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Actively exploited vulnerabilities and severe security incidents are reported within 24h&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;product-classification&#34;&gt;Product classification&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;core functionality&amp;rdquo; of the product determines the product classification. Majority of the products in scope of the CRA belong to the &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo; class. These are all products categories that are not explicitly mentioned by the CRA as important or critical products.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The are two classes of &amp;ldquo;important products&amp;rdquo; listed by the regulation: Class I and Class II, plus additional group of &amp;ldquo;critical products&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cra_product_classes.png&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;conformity-assessment&#34;&gt;Conformity assessment&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Only products that belong to the default and Class I categories are allowed to be self assessed by the manufacturer, follow the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;module A&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; assessment. The self assessment of a Class I product is only possible if the harmonized standard providing presumption of conformity for the specific Class I product category exist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The assessment of other product categories needs to involve &lt;a href=&#34;https://single-market-economy.ec.europa.eu/single-market/goods/building-blocks/notified-bodies_en&#34;&gt;Notified Body&lt;/a&gt; (NB) and follow &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;module B+C&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Another option is to follow the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;module H&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and perform process assessment with a NB to certify that the processes followed by the manufacturer ensure any product produced by the manufacturer is CRA compliant.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cra_assessment_modules.png&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the product classification the manufacturer may always decide to involve a NB in the product assessment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;standards&#34;&gt;Standards&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A number of CRA related standards were requested to be developed in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ec.europa.eu/growth/tools-databases/enorm/mandate/606_en&#34;&gt;standardization request&lt;/a&gt;. This includes three &amp;ldquo;horizontal&amp;rdquo; standards addressing process, vulnerabilities handling and catalog of controls plus a number of &amp;ldquo;vertical&amp;rdquo; standards requested for each of the important product classes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All requested standards are to be harmonized and some of them (vulnerability handling and vertical standards) are expected also to provide presumption of conformity allowing manufacture to perform self assessment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;product-evaluation-flow&#34;&gt;Product evaluation flow&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first step in the product evaluation is the definition of the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;core functionality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; of the product. This important step determines the class of the product and what assessment module can be followed but also what specifications can be considered applicable.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cra_product_evaluation.png&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer of a product of the default class has a freedom to select any assessment module and use any specifications providing that they cover all CRA requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;product-assessment&#34;&gt;Product assessment&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to prove the conformity with the CRA the manufacturer needs to be in a position to demonstrate that the processes is employed ensuring the product is secure and the security of the product (compliance with the CRA) is maintained over the lifetime of the product. This includes all obligations listed by the CRA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While the manufacturer has the freedom to select any specification/criteria to achieve the compliance with the CRA the best approach is to follow the specifications that are being developed by European standardization organizations &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cencenelec.eu/news-events/news/2025/newsletter/ots-62-cra/&#34;&gt;CEN-CENELEC&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.etsi.org/newsroom/press-releases/2545-etsi-leverages-global-technical-expertise-to-support-the-eu-cyber-resilience-act&#34;&gt;ETSI&lt;/a&gt;. These specifications are developed to cover the full scope of the CRA including processes, product requirements and all product classes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;relevant-links&#34;&gt;Relevant links&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2024/2847/oj/eng&#34;&gt;Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ec.europa.eu/growth/tools-databases/enorm/mandate/606_en&#34;&gt;CRA Standardization Request&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://single-market-economy.ec.europa.eu/single-market/goods/building-blocks/notified-bodies_en&#34;&gt;Notified Bodies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=oj:JOC_2022_247_R_0001&#34;&gt;Blue Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
